Sylvia Fein
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Sylvia Fein papers
1936-2011
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Fein, Sylvia
5.9 linear feet
The papers of painter and author Sylvia Fein measure 5.9 linear feet and date from 1936 to 2011. The papers primarily document her friendships with other artists from the Wisconsin-based Magic Realist group, including Dudley Huppler, John Wilde, Marshall Glasier, and Karl Priebe, as well as her career as a painter and her work on the books Heidi's Horse and First Drawings: Genesis of Visual Thinking. Documentation consists of scattered biographical material, extensive correspondence, project files, writings by Huppler and others, printed material, photographs, artwork by Wilde and Glasier, and scrapbooks.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 2011 by Sylvia Fein.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Sylvia Fein (1919- ) is a painter and author in Martinez, California. She is part of the Magic Realist Group of artists that originated at the University of Wisconsin.
Fein was born in Milwaukee, Wisconsin, and from 1938 to 1942 she studied art at the University of Wisconsin in Madison. While there she became friends with fellow artists Marshall Glasier, John Wilde, Dudley Huppler, and Karl Priebe. In 1942 she married William Scheuber and briefly had a factory job in Milwaukee testing switches for naval planes. From 1944 to 1947 Fein lived and traveled throughout Mexico. Much of the work produced during this period was included in a solo exhibition of her paintings at the Perls Galleries in 1946. She and her husband then moved to northern California and had a daughter, Heidi. During the 1950s and 1960s, Fein continued to paint in her home studio.
In 1973 Fein decided to take a break from painting and published two books, Heidi's Horse (1976) and First Drawings: Genesis of Visual Thinking (1993). These works were greatly inspired by her friendship with art educator and researcher, Henry Shaefer-Simmern. In 2003 she resumed painting. She was featured in the group show, "With Friends: Six Magic Realists, 1940-1965" at the University of Wisconsin in 2005 and in a solo retrospective at the Bakersfield Art Museum in 2007. From 1970 to 2000 Fein was also active in the community of Pleasant Hill, California, as a member of several public services commissions.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter and author Sylvia Fein measure 5.9 linear feet and date from 1936 to 2011. The papers primarily document her friendships with other artists from the Wisconsin-based Magic Realist group, including Dudley Huppler, John Wilde, Marshall Glasier, and Karl Priebe, as well as her career as a painter and her work on the books Heidi's Horse and First Drawings: Genesis of Visual Thinking. Documentation consists of scattered biographical material, extensive correspondence, project files, writings by Huppler and others, printed material, photographs, artwork by Wilde and Glasier, and scrapbooks.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 8 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1936-2010 (Box 1, 8; 10 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1941-2011 (Box 1-3; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Project Files, 1970-2011 (Box 3-4, 8; 1.2 linear feet)
Series 4: Writings by Others, circa 1940s-1994 (Box 4; 4 folders)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1941-2010 (Box 4-5; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1940-2000 (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, 1941-1947 (Box 5; 3 folders)
Series 8: Scrapbooks, circa 1940-2010 (Box 5-7; 0.8 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Authors--California; Authors--Wisconsin; Magic realism (Art); Painters--California; Painters-Wisconsin--Madison; Women artists--California; Women artists--Wisconsin
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks
Names:
Glasier, Marshall, 1902-; Huppler, Dudley, 1917-1988; Priebe, Karl J., 1914-1976; Wilde, John, 1919-2006
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1936-2010, Series 1:; (Box 1, 8; 10 folders)
  Found here are scattered biographical documents including a guest book from an exhibition, Fein's high school yearbook, a chronology, draft documents and layouts for her website, and documents from presentation on Fein's life using kinesthetic modeling.
  - Chronology, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documentation for Sylvia Fein Website, circa 2008-2009, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Guest Book, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Kinesthetic Modeling Presentation, circa 2000, 2004, (Oversized items housed in box 8) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Maxwell Galleries Consignments and Sales, 1962-1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Web Search Print-outs, 2007-2010 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Yearbook, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Kinesthetic Modeling Presentation, circa 2000, 2004, (Oversized items from box 1, folder 5) (Box 8)
- Correspondence, 1941-2011, Series 2:; (Box 1-3; 2.3 linear feet)
  Correspondence, some illustrated, includes letters and postcards from friends and collegues Marshall Glasier, John and Shirley Wilde, Dudley Huppler, Karl Priebe, Helen Ashman, Lee Hoiby, Klaus Perls, and Henry Shaefer-Simmern among others. Most correspondence in this series is of a personal, rather than professional nature, and the bulk of these letters date from the 1990s-2000s. Of note are almost daily letters in the form of mail art from Fein's husband's oncologist, Randall Oyer. Researchers should note that additional correspondence is included within Series 8: Scrapbooks.
  Letters have been arranged alphabetically by last name. Letters from individuals who had correspondence with Fein of four letters or less are found within the miscellaneous folders.
  - Sylvia Fein Letters to Family, 1960, 1965, 1968, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Ashman, Helen, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Cozzolino, Robert, 2001-2010, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Dadian, Arnold, 1944, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Dissanayake, Ellen, 1997-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dreyfus, John, 1997-2001 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Duncan, Michael, 2006-2008 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ezell, Carol, 2008-2009 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Gilmore, Bob, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Glasier, Marshall, circa 1942-1963, 1974-1975, (8 folders) (Box 1, Folder 25-32)
  - Graber, Sheila, 2005-2011 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Hoiby, Lee, 1952, 1969, circa 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Huppler, Dudley, 1941-1973, (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 35-44)
  - Huppler, Dudley, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Huppler, Dudley - Undated Letters, circa 1942-1987, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 46-49)
  - Miller, Florence, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Mody, Zarin, circa 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Neumeyer, Peter, circa 1963-1999 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Oyer, Randall, 2006-2011, (21 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-21)
  - Partch, Harry, 1951-1964 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Perls Galleries, 1943-1949, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Priebe, Karl, 1944-1975 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Schaefer-Simmern, Henry and Gertrude, 1956-1973 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Scheuber, Heidi, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Vivas, Eliseo and Dorothy, circa 1957-1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Whitnah, Kerwin, circa 1971-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Wilde, John, 1942-1966, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Wilde, John, 1991-2006, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Wilde, Shirley, circa 2007-2008 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wilson, Frank, circa 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Winters-Montemayor, Elizabeth, 2007-2010 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, A-B, 1972-2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous, C, 1987-2009 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, D, 1974, circa 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, F-G, 1955-2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, H-K, circa 1962-2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, L-M, circa 1964-2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, N-R, circa 1966-2003 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, S, circa 1956-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous, T-W, 1953-2001 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Unidentified, First Names Only, circa 1964-2005, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
- Project Files, 1970-2011, Series 3:; (Box 3-4, 8; 1.2 linear feet)
  Found here are files maintained by Sylvia Fein for various projects. Files for her two book projects, Heidi's Horse (1976) and First Drawings: Genesis of Visual Thinking (1993), include extensive correspondence, permission requests, photographs of the writing and publication process, film proposals, and press clippings. Materials regarding both books are filed together. Also found are project files for Fein's participation in Pleasant Hill, California, public services. Included are records of her work on the Architectural Review Commission and her 1980 run for city council. Project files for the opening of the Rosie the Riveter/World War II Home Fron National Historical Park include photographs, correspondence, a biographical statement, and press materials.
  This series also includes project files documenting Fein's retrospective "Wondrous Life: Paintings and Drawings by Sylvia Fein," at the Bakersfield Art Museum in 2007. Included are correspondence, exhibition photographs, planning documents, and the exhibition catalogs and announcements.
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Heidi's Horse and First Drawings, 1970-2011
  Subseries 3.2: Pleasant Hill Public Services, 1970-2008
  Subseries 3.3: Rosie the Riveter National Historic Park, 2002-2010
  Subseries 3.4: "Wondrous Life: Paintings and Drawings by Sylvia Fein," 2006-2008
  - Heidi's Horse and First Drawings, 1970-2011, 3.1:
    - Correspondence, "Looking for a Publisher," 1970-1974, 1985-1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1974-2011, (13 folders) (Box 3, Folder 23-35)
    - "Daily Log" Notebook, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Donata Elschenbroich Film Project, 2000-2005 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Film Proposal, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Permission Requests and Photograph Orders, 1976-2001, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
    - Photographs, 1972-1990s (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Press Clippings, 1976-2009 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Press Clippings, 1976-2009, (5 folders; oversized items housed in box 8) (Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    - Oversized Press Clippings, 1976-2009, (Oversized items from box 4, folders 1-5) (Box 8)
  - Pleasant Hill Public Services, 1970-2008, 3.2:
    - Architectural Review Commission, 1970, 1981-2008, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 6-9)
    - City Council Election, 1980, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
    - Fee Abitration Program, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous Records, 1979-circa 2001 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Photographs, circa 1979-2000, 2002, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 14-16)
  - Rosie the Riveter National Historic Park, 2002-2010, 3.3:
    - Rosie the Riveter National Historic Park, 2002-2010, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 17-20)
  - "Wondrous Life: Paintings and Drawings by Sylvia Fein,"2006-2008, 3.4:
    - Correspondence, 2007-2008 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Photographs, circa 2007 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Planning Documents, 2006-2007 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Writings by Others, circa 1940s-1994, Series 4:; (Box 4; 4 folders)
  Found here is a dissertation on Henry Schaefer-Simmern and a draft outline written by Schaefer-Simmern. Also found are several short writings by Dudley Huppler.
  - Dissertation by Raymond C. Berta, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Writings by Dudley Huppler, circa 1940s, 1987, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 26-27)
  - Chapter Outline from The Essence of Form by Henry Schaefer-Simmern, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Printed Material, 1941-2010, Series 5:; (Box 4-5; 0.7 linear feet)
  Printed material consists of books, including two written by Sylvia Fein, magazines and news clippings documenting her activities, and a few exhibition catalog and announcements, primarily from her early career. Also found are files of printed material which Fein compiled to document the careers of her friends and fellow artists including Marshall Glasier, John Wilde, Dudley Huppler, and Karl Priebe. These files contain exhibition announcements, catalogs, and news clippings. Researchers should note that a large amount of printed material is also found within Series 8: Scrapbooks.
  - Book, Consciousness of Artistic Form by Henry Schaefer-Simmern, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Book, First Drawings: Genesis of Visual Thinking by Sylvia Fein, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Book, Heidi's Horse by Sylvia Fein, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Book, The Lesson Book by Dudley Huppler, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1943-2005, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Map of Europe, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Magazines, 1946, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1960-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Newsletter, The Echoboard, 1957-1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Printed Material regarding Marshall Glasier, circa 1941-2008, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 8-10)
  - Printed Material regarding Dudley Huppler, 1944-2007 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Printed Material regarding Harry Partch, circa 1952-2005, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 12-14)
  - Printed Material regarding Karl Priebe, 1944-1977 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Printed Material regarding Henry Schaefer-Simmern, 1952-1977 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Printed Material regarding John Wilde, circa 1948-2010, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 17-19)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1960-2009, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-21)
- Photographs, circa 1940-2000, Series 6:; (Box 5; 0.2 linear feet)
  Found here are one photograph of Sylvia Fein with John Wilde and photocopies of photographs of Fein and her husband William Scheuber during World War II. The bulk of the photographs depict other artists including Dudley Huppler, Marshall Glasier, and Karl Priebe, as well as artwork by Marshall Glasier and John Wilde. Included within the photographs of Dudley Huppler are group photographs depicting Huppler with Gertrude Abercrombie, Karl Priebe, and John Wilde. Two portraits of Dudley Huppler were taken by George Platt Lynes and Carl Van Vechten. Researchers should note that additional photographs of Sylvia Fein are found within Series 8: Scrapbooks.
  - Sylvia Fein and William Scheuber (Photocopies), circa 1940-1946 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Sylvia Fein and John Wilde, circa 1941 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Dudley Huppler, circa 1945-1972, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 24-26)
  - Marshall Glasier, circa 1950s-1968 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Marshall Glasier, Artwork, circa 1955-1968, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - Marshall Glasier, Negatives, 1955, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Karl Priebe, circa 1940s, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Henry Schaefer-Simmern, circa 1972 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - John Wilde, Artwork, 1967-2000 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- Artwork, 1941-1947, Series 7:; (Box 5; 3 folders)
  Included are pencil drawings by Marshall Glasier and John Wilde and one oil painting on board by John Wilde called The Raven and the Fox.
  - Drawings by Marshall Glasier, circa 1943-1947 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Drawings by John Wilde, circa 1944 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Painting by John Wilde, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Scrapbooks, circa 1940-2010, Series 8:; (Box 5-7; 0.8 linear feet)
  Scrapbooks were created by Sylvia Fein to document her career and activities from 1940 to the present. Included are letters, newpaper clippings, exhibition catalogs and announcements, price lists for works of art, and photographs.
  Scrapbook materials have been removed from binders and plastic binder sleeves and housed in archival folders. The original order of the documents has been maintained.
  - Scrapbook "1940-1945", circa 1940-1945, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 37-39)
  - Scrapbook "1945-1950", circa 1945-1950, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 40-41)
  - Scrapbook "1951-1960", circa 1950-1961, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 42-43)
  - Scrapbook "1951-1960", circa 1950-1961 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook "1961-1965", circa 1960-1965, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 2-5)
  - Scrapbook "1966-2000", circa 1966-2000, (4 folders) (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
  - Scrapbook "2001-2004", circa 2000-2004 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Scrapbook "2001-2004", circa 2000-2004 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook "2004-2006", circa 2002-2006, (3 folders) (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  - Scrapbook "2006-present", circa 2006-2010, (2 folders) (Box 7, Folder 5-6)